<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://earmarkspod.com/</id>
  <title><![CDATA[Earmarks]]></title>
  <subtitle><![CDATA[Out-of-print book reviews]]></subtitle>
  <icon>https://earmarkspod.com/favicon.png</icon>
  <link href="https://earmarkspod.com" />
  <link href="https://earmarkspod.com/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <updated>2023-02-09T20:52:58.863Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Earmarks Podcast]]></name>
  </author>
  <category term="sci-fi" scheme="https://earmarkspod.com/?tags=sci-fi" />
  <category term="1960s" scheme="https://earmarkspod.com/?tags=1960s" />
  <category term="Aliens" scheme="https://earmarkspod.com/?tags=Aliens" />
  <category term="Intergalactic Travel" scheme="https://earmarkspod.com/?tags=Intergalactic%20Travel" />
  <category term="Moon (Lunar)" scheme="https://earmarkspod.com/?tags=Moon%20(Lunar)" />
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[002 - Way Station by Clifford D. Simak]]></title>
    <link href="https://earmarkspod.com/episodes/002-Way-Station" />
    <id>https://earmarkspod.com/episodes/002-Way-Station</id>
    <published>2023-02-01T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-09T20:52:17.460Z</updated>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<h2 id="book-info"><a href="#book-info">Book Info</a></h2><ul><li>published in 1963</li><li>originally in TWO parts, published in Galaxy Magazine (June and August 1963 issues) under the title <em>‘Here Gather the Stars’</em>.</li><li>Last printed (in English) in 2015 (french in 2019)</li><li><a href="https://www.isfdb.org/cgi-bin/title.cgi?6698" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer external" target="_blank">ISFDB Page</a></li></ul><h3 id="my-personal-copy-info"><a href="#my-personal-copy-info">My Personal Copy Info</a></h3><p>I have the Easton Press leather bound edition of Way Station as printed in the ’80s, as well as the entire 1963 run of Galaxy Magazine, including the two issues containing <em>‘Here Gather the Stars’</em>.</p><p>The Easton Press edition is a lovely brown leather and gilded page edges. The cover design shows the house that the majority of the novel takes place in and around. as well as a delightful rendition of some of the travelers that stopped by the Station on the inside cover pages.</p><p>(images incoming)</p><p>The two issues of Galaxy Magazine include custom illustrations on each cover that have nothing specific to do with <em>‘Here Gather the Stars’</em>, but are nonetheless gorgeous cover designs themselves.</p><p>(images incoming)</p><hr><h2 id="a-brief-history"><a href="#a-brief-history">A Brief History</a></h2><p>This book was (surprisingly) released originally in TWO parts, published in Galaxy Magazine in 1963, under the Title ‘Here Gather the Stars’ which in my opinion is a better and more fitting name than Way Station, even though Way Station is more ‘intriguing’ and hooking as a title.</p><p>It has since been reprinted and translated in more than a dozen languages, and is widely considered a venerable classic among science fiction.</p><hr><h2 id="spoiler-free-review"><a href="#spoiler-free-review">Spoiler FREE Review</a></h2><p>Way Station is generally a quiet contemplative novel about loneliness and the nature of what it means to be a human on earth. It Follows Enoch Wallace, who is the sole operator of an intergalactic travel station on Earth. Simak is the type of person who genuinely believed in the goodness of human nature and writes through a lens of compassion and generosity, so the entire book is permeated by unrelenting optimism, especially in the small details. This is a book for people that like the big questions sci-fi asks but need a break from the humbling, hopeless, and generally dire lens that those questions often get asked through in the genre. </p><p>Way Station does not shy away from looking directly at large issues of ableism, domestic abuse and even some political allegory while maintaining the opinion throughout that humanity is ultimately good and worthwhile. This is a classic for a reason and deserves its (somewhat forgotten) place in the annuls of history on the same bookshelf as To Kill a Mockingbird and Slaughterhouse Five.</p><hr><h2 id="spoiler-filled-review"><a href="#spoiler-filled-review">Spoiler FILLED Review</a></h2><p>This is a story about the loneliness and solitude of Enoch Wallace in his duty to both the galaxy and to earth and humanity and non-humanity all at once. </p><p>To reiterate, this book is great. it stands up to inspection and re-reading extremely well and is full of the sort of nuance, criticism and subtlety that firmly place it in the Great Scifi Classic conversation. Enoch carries with him a specific note of introspection that we dont often see. He looks inside himself often and without reservation, there are no hidden dark corners of his mind that he keeps from looking directly at. He is not ashamed, or closemouthed about the war he was involved in and how that shaped him. He does not try to hide the barbarism of humanity from the aliens, even though he tries hard to avoid them seeing it, lest they think this is the only aspect of humanity. Enoch Wallace is a GOOD PERSON and Simak does an absolutely wonderful job of leading us to that conclusion throughout the book. he doesnt come out and say it, or show Enoch saving a cat, he just writes in such a way to outline the good-natured thinking and actions Enoch partakes in for the length of the novel.</p><p>We get to see some great Scifi tech and ideas on display, especially for 1963. for example, the ‘VR’ type simulation described in Enoch’s basement is like a perfect end goal dream VR setup. the entire room is transformed including SCENT and is indistinguishable from being physically teleported to the location, Enoch even uses his real rifle and the walls simply absorb the bullets he fires.VR without a headset is top tier, and more than a DECADE before star trek did the holodeck. </p><p>This book also portrays teleportation in my favorite way as well, its not an uncommon type of teleportation (though this might be among the first to think of it this way). Where the body is effectively transferred to a new location as data, rebuilt anew in that new location, and the old body is ‘disposed of’ now being effectively an empty chunk of meat. this is actually similar to the initial premise of the book im currently writing, and this type of teleportation is the only one that ever made any sort of sense to me. </p><p>Some of my favorite scenes in this novel are used to show different sides of Enoch, and they are all good sides. we dont get to see any ‘bad’ side of Enoch during this novel. For example, when we first meet Lucy, its clear from the get go that Lucy and Enoch have a proper companionship thats not romantic, its never even hinted that that is an option. It is just a platonic love where they clearly have affection for each other that is deep and understanding and utterly non-romantic. its a shining example of a healthy way to interact with human beings, which is a through-line of this book. Enoch treats everyone (human and non-human) with unwavering respect, and compassion. So much so that it is actually a plot point in the novel itself. There is repeated attention given to a particular grave stone and its circumstances that is sort of like checkov’s gravestone. it plays a role in the initial hook of the novel, where at the end of chapter 3 we get this gravestone as a cliffhanger, where Lewis is investigating Enoch’s property to find clues as to what is going on here and the chapter ends with ‘there were just the names and dates. On the first stone: Amanda Wallace, on the second stone: Jedediah Wallace, and on the third stone…”  which excellently draws us into the question of…WHO exactly is Enoch, is he dead? meant to be dead? what could that third stone possibly mean?? and about halfway through the book we learn that third stone is actually marked with an alien language, WHAT!? then we immediately get the backstory of what happened, where a Hazer and new/good friend of Enoch comes to the station on his travels and dies while there, and Enoch is told to handle it according to local custom, so what he does is wait all night, take the body out and bury it in his family’s plot right next to his parents because he has so much love and respect for the Hazer people and their culture and the individuals he has met over the decades. which is wonderful and brings new respect to Enoch as a character. We are meant to believe the alien writing was simply the Hazer’s name, like we might expect to find on a human gravestone. later we find out that the body has been removed from its grave, and because of that snafu the earth station is likely to be shut down, and a delegate from the hazer community is coming to issue a formal protest. while the hazer is there, Enoch respects the protest but asks that they respect the human need to ‘see for themselves’ even though the hazer’s know that that body has been moved. Enoch goes to the gravesite and the Hazer delegate asks to follow. upon seeing the gravestone and reading its inscription the Hazer is deeply moved. Enoch decides he NEEDS to get the body back and restore what is right, leading the Hazer delegate to perhaps allow this wrong to be righted at least. after the climax of the novel, we finally get this inscription deciphered for us, thus paying off the checkov’s gun. it reads “Here lies one from a distant star, but soil is not alien to him, for in death he belongs to the universe.” </p><p>which frankly, is just beautiful and i see why the Hazer felt like Enoch truly understood and was trying his best to pay respects to their culture and all of the galaxy at the same time. it is a gloriously written thread showcasing Enoch’s mental state throughout the grieving process and trying to navigate the intricacies of galactic cultural politics.</p><p>its one of literally DOZENS of glimpses in this novel that color in the shades of Enoch Wallace, and and show us that he is a good person, and the people around him are good. this novel is an essay about non-toxic humanity, but it gets into deep philosophy like we might expect from scifi as well. we get plenty of ‘what does is mean to be human?’ which is a welcome, if not common question in the genre, but we also get more esoteric points. like a metaphor for how governments should all have term limits and age limits. in Chapter 30 right after Enoch gets out of the dope ass VR simulation time he has a realization and dilemma about his ability to be the sole representative for Earth to the Galactic Confraternity. he has lived so long isolated and unaging in this station, being almost entirely separated from the human race except for a few choice friends and contacts over the years, and he feels like he CAN no longer represent the earth because of that. he says “He was a man of the 19th century, and being as such how could he possibly represent the 20th? How much does the human character change with each generation, and over a lifetime?” which is an incredibly insightful thought process and i think points to the fact that he IS a good representative for humanity. its the same as the old saying ‘the right person to be King, doesnt want the crown.’ which is heavily hinted at, and a thinly veiled allegory for the lifetime appointments of some government officials, and how the leadership of the country, and often the world, are too wealthy, spent too long separate from the struggles of the common person and is too out of touch with the population to truly be good representatives of that population.</p><p>Lastly toward the end of the novel, at the end of Chapter 33, we get yet another wonderful insight into human nature through the lens of Enoch Wallace Good Person (tm). Lucy’s dad Hank, who is not a very good person all told, is seen running down the hill screaming, fleeing from the light of the Talisman which is meant to bring peace and stability and clarity to everything in the galaxy. Enoch remarks ‘I am sorry we frightened him, No man should be afraid of this.” and Winslowe says ‘its himself he is afraid of, that man lives with a terror in him.” and Enoch thinks “thats the way with Man; it had always been the way. He ahd carried terror with him, and the thing he was afraid of had always been himself.” which is a kind way of stating one of the natures of abuse, but it also goes to further highlight Enoch’s separation from society. Only to the reader, and only in retrospect do we see that Enoch is set apart in this as well. We see throughout the novel that Enoch is not afraid of the unknown or of what needs doing, or addressing. its why there is no dark corners of his character and why he can and does stand up for the ‘little guy’ throughout the novel. he isnt afraid of facing things full in the face and dealing with them, which sets him apart from a large portion of human nature, but is, i think, an aspect many of us strive towards in much of our life.</p><p>Way Station is a wonderful novel and has much more to say than what i can cover here in a timely fashion. if you made it this far without reading it, i hope my spoilers werent too much that you dont pick this novel up, because it is truly a classic of Science Fiction and you should read it.</p><h3 id="criticisms"><a href="#criticisms">Criticisms</a></h3><p>now on to my only criticisms with this novel. they are short and simple and i wont spend much time on them, firstly, this novel can switch from a ‘matter of fact’ style of prose and structure, to a really poetic and metaphorical style rapidly, and often. which can be somewhat disorientating if youre not ready for that sort of thing. secondly, the tertiary characters just accept alien life…almost instantly without much hesitation, which is more than a little unrealistic. granted they were both sort of ‘primed’ on the fact for years now, with Winslowe getting a lot of alien wood that he says no one he asked about has ever seen before and is perfect for making things etc. And with Lewis who has spent a handful of years now hunting down this story and learning as much as he can about ‘the 130 year old who looks 35” and how his house cant be interacted with etc. so they had suspicions but when they are both faced full on with the truth of alien life, they basically never mention it or even seem bothered. its as if they both just met some guy named Bob thats a friend of Enoch’s and that was that. </p><hr><h2 id="watch-or-listen-here"><a href="#watch-or-listen-here">Watch or Listen Here</a></h2><iframe src="https://redcircle.com/embedded-player/sh/bf11c8f9-3c8e-4125-9a8a-6b36e97c1379/ep/e9138bbb-efa1-4779-847b-48a7812797f2" class="redcircle-player" title="RedCircle Episode Player" frameborder="0" loading="lazy" scrolling="no" height="170" width="750" allowfullscreen></iframe><div class="relative pb-[56.25%] mb-4"><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/oU3CRHbCtBU?autoplay=0&amp;disablekb=0&amp;controls=1&amp;fs=1&amp;loop=0" class="absolute w-full h-full" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>]]>
    </content>
    <category term="sci-fi" scheme="https://earmarkspod.com/?tags=sci-fi" />
    <category term="1960s" scheme="https://earmarkspod.com/?tags=1960s" />
    <category term="Aliens" scheme="https://earmarkspod.com/?tags=Aliens" />
    <category term="Intergalactic Travel" scheme="https://earmarkspod.com/?tags=Intergalactic%20Travel" />
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[001 - A Fall of Moondust by Arthur C. Clarke]]></title>
    <link href="https://earmarkspod.com/episodes/001-A-Fall-Of-Moondust" />
    <id>https://earmarkspod.com/episodes/001-A-Fall-Of-Moondust</id>
    <published>2023-01-08T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-09T20:52:17.460Z</updated>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<h2 id="book-info"><a href="#book-info">Book Info</a></h2><ul><li>published in 1961</li><li>usually between 224 and 256 pages</li><li>translated to 10 total languages</li><li>originally printed in hardcover first, and was reprinted in paperback every 3-5 years from release until its final printing in 2012 (except for specialty imprints)</li><li><a href="https://www.isfdb.org/cgi-bin/title.cgi?1969" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer external" target="_blank">ISFDB Page</a></li></ul><h3 id="my-personal-copy-info"><a href="#my-personal-copy-info">My Personal Copy Info</a></h3><p>I have a version of this book printed in 1963, for the <em>Science Fiction Book Club of London</em>. A hardcover book, it has a custom designed dust jacket cover, with a beautiful abstract blue and white planet-shaped pattern on both sides.</p><p>(photos incoming)</p><hr><h2 id="a-brief-history"><a href="#a-brief-history">A Brief History</a></h2><ul><li>A Fall of Moondust was nominated for a hugo award, as an honorable mention in the 1962 hugo awards, and as a finalist in the 1963 hugo awards, but lost</li><li>It had a radio drama adaptation on BBC Radio, released in 1981. (I desperately need to hear this)</li><li>the vast majority of its prints and translation prints were in the 1980’s.</li><li>This novel voiced a major fear and uncertainty about the unknowns of landing on the moon at the time, almost a decade before we actually did it for the first time. we did not know if the moon was solid enough to land on at all, or if Buzz and Neil would simply sink into it like in the novel. we had a pretty good idea it would be fine (obviously hence why we sent people) but it was still uncertain even when Apollo 11 launched.</li></ul><hr><h2 id="spoiler-free-review"><a href="#spoiler-free-review">Spoiler FREE Review</a></h2><p>A Fall of Moondust is a joy of a book, feels like a subtle mix between the Martian and 12 Angry Men. It follows a small voyage cruise aboard the Lunar Dust-Cruiser Selene on a sea of regolith named the Sea of Thirst. Drama ensues with and to the small party onboard and they must get to know each other, and work together to overcome the situation. Which sounds generic, and from a 10000ft view, it might be, but thats part of what makes this books such a wonderful read. its a ‘small scope’ story. it doesnt span lightyears or decades. its a small group, on a small boat, with high stakes to them, not the universe. </p><p>With every descriptor and line of dialog it is clear this is a work by Arthur C. Clarke, his narrative voice is absolutely crystalline in all his works, and might as well be a tuning fork with how easy it is to discern. It is also clear that this is a book written before the moon landings. some of the ideas postulated by Clarke are uncanny in their accuracy for a modern post-space society, and some of them are quaint and adorable, which we will discuss more in the spoiler section of this review. suffice it to say if you want to stop now and read this book before i get into spoilers, i can highly recommend it. its the perfect book for when you need a small story. i found it absolutely lovely in between giant fantasy epic series, as a sort of palette cleanser. </p><hr><h2 id="spoiler-filled-review"><a href="#spoiler-filled-review">Spoiler FILLED Review</a></h2><p>I find that this book is exactly what i need when i find myself overwhelmed or burnt out, or just too tired to emotionally deal with the intensity of other more modern books. As the crew and passengers find themselves stranded beneath the regolith, the stakes are incredibly high for them but the intensity is not high for us, the readers. i love that. i get really anxious sometimes when im reading other stories and people are dying and the last life boat gets blown up and all that sort of drama. But here, the drama is well written but not as intense, which is a rarity. for example, part way through the story they begin building up the ‘weird and silent new zealander’ who the captain and commodore have identified as potentially troublesome. when that bomb finally lands, its not that he is someone who has cracked and decided to sabotage the ship’s repair efforts or kill everyone onboard or anything. its that he is convinced this whole thing is his fault because aliens are after him. he is a deep conspiracy theorist and believes this is aliens stopping him from finding some secret he was nearing. thats good drama, but its medium intensity at best, this book was like a breath of air in the extreme drama of a lot of scifi books.</p><p>In the end, they all get out alive and well, putting this traumatic and harrowing experience behind them, just like regular people would. they survived a vacation catastrophe and moved on,. Which is utterly delightful to read, as macabre as that sounds. Clarke has a way with his narrative to make the story feel good, worthwhile and dramatic without needing to resort to the a lot of what I now feel is cliche. Thats exactly why i was expecting that person to start killing or exploding things, instead of the more obvious reality-facing thing that he is just a conspiracy theorist, like you would find on a public bus instead of an intergalactic super villain. This book’s happy ending is also well deserved, these people fought and sacrificed and survived and we DONT get the rug pulled out from under us after that, like i would expect (and did expect here) in a modern novel. I relished the epilogue even more so because i did expect the rug to be pulled out and for Captain Pat to die saving the others, but instead he makes it out alive. He uses the realization of his love for Sue Wilkins, the stewardess, to help move on with his life, marry her and start to have children. He begins training a replacement captain for the cruise voyage so he can retire, and makes on last trip on the Sea of Thirst to officially commemorate and handoff that duty, and STILL he makes it out just fine, with nary a sentence about the voyage other than to say it was good to be back on last time before saying goodbye forever.</p><p>I felt that the characters were all very well thought out, and fleshed out, even though we dont spend much time with each of them individually aside from Commodore Hansteen, Captain Pat Harris, Sue Wilkins (the stewardess) and Aboriginal Australian Physicist Duncan McKenzie. each of whom was fascinating to learn about. Pat and Duncan have a fascinating conversation about his aboriginal heritage and how he feels about the ‘white settlers’ of australia sort of taking over the and mostly destroying their ways in an effort to ‘modernize the savages’. and that conversation is treated delicately, and with wonderful tact. when that convo started i began to sort of cringe, probably out of habit from being on the internet so long, but it turned out to be lovely and informative and interesting with no sense of BS. Commodore Hansteen as well is a retired SUPERSTAR of the universe basically, stepping on tons of planets and leading the first ever expedition to Pluto. He has lead a storied and full career and has since retired. He is traveling under an alias and has shaved his iconic beard which is why no one noticed him onboard or on the manifest until the accident occurred and he had to ‘come clean’ and work ALONGSIDE Pat Harris to command the situation and help keep the passengers from panic, all the while making sure not to overshadow Pat’s captain-age and undermine his authority. </p><p>There is also a delightful amount ‘clearly 1960s ideas’ which are great contrast to some of the ideas in the same chapters that are so modern its crazy. for example, the electric and liquid oxygen fueled Selene ship, is full of really modern ideas about how vehicles will work in the ‘future’ (ie right about now) but also all information is sent via a ‘telephone-like’ system and printed out. so the ship is waiting on a passenger manifest to be sent over so they can verify who is on board, but instead of just showing the list on screen, it has to be printed and read by someone else, who then informs the base commander. there are more obvious things as well, like an entire crate of cigarettes being on board alongside the food rations etc, but there are also much more modern ideas too, like a scientist hosting a ‘talk/debate’ show online from the moon, debunking and arguing with audience members on earth about possible solutions to get Selene out of the crater. its a delightful mix of old-timey and very modern that can only come out of top tier mid-century sci-fi.</p><p>i will continue to pull this book out occasionally when i need a break and a breather, and an unabashedly happy ending with no caveats. Just good clean hard scifi drama, which is a highlight to why Arthur C. Clarke is a master. </p><h3 id="criticisms"><a href="#criticisms">Criticisms</a></h3><p>the only criticism I really have with this novel is it sometimes lingers a little too long on weird dead ends in the narrative, in an effort to build out the world.</p><hr><h2 id="watch-or-listen-here"><a href="#watch-or-listen-here">Watch or Listen Here</a></h2><iframe src="https://redcircle.com/embedded-player/sh/bf11c8f9-3c8e-4125-9a8a-6b36e97c1379/ep/589bafd5-c0a7-49e6-b331-71ecf56cca32" class="redcircle-player" title="RedCircle Episode Player" frameborder="0" loading="lazy" scrolling="no" height="170" width="750" allowfullscreen></iframe><div class="relative pb-[56.25%] mb-4"><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ejArWyQgEN8?autoplay=0&amp;disablekb=0&amp;controls=1&amp;fs=1&amp;loop=0" class="absolute w-full h-full" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>]]>
    </content>
    <category term="sci-fi" scheme="https://earmarkspod.com/?tags=sci-fi" />
    <category term="1960s" scheme="https://earmarkspod.com/?tags=1960s" />
    <category term="Moon (Lunar)" scheme="https://earmarkspod.com/?tags=Moon%20(Lunar)" />
  </entry>
</feed>